lottery.ie 2018-08-31

# Data Privacy Statement | Useful Info | Irish National Lottery

#### Player Registration

**Personal data processed**

Gender, name, preferred greeting, address, email address, date of birth, proof of ID, IP address, date and time of registration, credit or debit card, browser, mother’s maiden name, place of birth, emailing preferences, URLs visited, referral URLs.

**Purpose for processing and uses of the data**

To register a National Lottery Player in compliance with legal & regulatory requirements (living in Ireland, over 18 and responsible player).

To enable your ability to play, PLI requires the storage of your credit or debit card with a nominated third party".

To send weekly results, inform of large jackpots, to receive information about offers and promotions.

**Lawful basis for processing the data**

The processing of data is necessary to enter into a contract with PLI and to meet the legal and regulatory requirements of the National Lottery Act and the Licence to Operate the National Lottery. If the player does not provide the requested data, PLI will not be able to complete the player registration.

Direct marketing activity is subject to player consent. The player has the clear option to opt-in to receive marketing communications at registration time and then to opt-out any time.

**Sharing of personal data**

PLI shares personal data with:

  * Camelot Global Services (CGS): management of PLI digital channels, customer care, IT.
  * Global Payments (formerly Realex Payments) to process your debit/credit card on behalf of PLI. Global Payments fully comply with the PCI/DSS 3.2 security requirements.
  * Adobe Campaign for marketing campaigns. Adobe Campaign is replacing HubSpot and will run in parallel until the end of September. Adobe Campaign stores personal data in Ireland.
  * HubSpot for marketing campaigns. HubSpot store personal data outside the EEA, in the USA. (EU-US Privacy Shield). HubSpot is being replaced by Adobe Campaign and all data held in HubSpot will be deleted after the migration process has been completed.
  * Intralot Ireland Limited (Intralot): maintenance of PLI’s players and retailers handling platforms and retailer terminals. Intralot staff are based on PLI premises.
  * Cloudflare to protect the National Lottery’s websites against DDoS attacks (Distributed Denial of Service, a type of hacking). This requires personal data to transit through Cloudflare’s infrastructure. This takes place in multiple locations both inside and outside the EEA (for transfers to the USA, EU-US Privacy Shield). The traffic through Cloudflare is fully-encrypted.
  * Google Analytics to measure the traffic on the National Lottery’s websites. See here for an overview of privacy at Google: (EU-US Privacy Shield and <https://support.google.com/analytics/answer/6004245>)
  * Display Media - DoubleClick (a Google product) offers technology products and services that are sold to Core Media (a nominated third party advertising agency) to allow the National Lottery to deploy, target, deliver, and report on interactive advertising campaigns.
  * Social Media - Audiences are set up on the National Lottery Facebook account based on HubSpot CRM (Customer Relationship Management) data. National Lottery also uses these audiences to market to other potential customers.
  * Kochava - Provides real-time attribution and analytics mobile tracking. It has integration with over 2,000 networks and publishers. Kochava is linked with DoubleClick to record the amount of downloads that are happening via National Lottery app campaigns supporting both iOS and Android. Kochava will track from download to registration and then report on the revenue that has been generated from that download via a player ID. (EU-US Privacy Shield and <https://www.kochava.com/> )
  * Tealium - The information collected by Tealium is used within our analytics tools to enrich the data we’re collecting about your visit in order to help us understand our visitors’ usage of the site so as to provide a better user experience.
  * Google AdWords - Google AdWords' system is based on cookies and keywords determined by advertisers. Google uses these characteristics to place National Lottery advertising on pages where they think it might be relevant. PLI pays when users divert their browsing to click on the National Lottery advertising.
  * Bing - which is a web search engine owned and operated by Microsoft. Similar to Google AdWords Bing system is based on cookies and keywords determined by advertisers.
  * In case of a complaint, the information may be shared with organisations who provide services to the company such as legal advisors.
  * Office of the Regulator of the National Lottery – the Regulator may access parts of this data in order to assess whether PLI is meeting its obligations to prevent underage or problem play.

#### Ongoing Player Interaction

**Personal data processed**

Gender, name, preferred greeting, address, email address, date of birth, proof of ID, IP address, date and time of visit, credit or debit card, browser, mother’s maiden name, place of birth, emailing preferences, URLs visited, referral URLs, games played, number played, amounts played, amounts added, amounts withdrawn, wallet amount, page, length of visit, cookies

**Purpose for processing and uses of the data**

To play any National Lottery game responsibly.

**Lawful basis for processing the data**

The processing of data is necessary to enter into a contract with PLI and to meet the legal and regulatory requirements of the National Lottery Act and the Licence to Operate the National Lottery. If the player does not provide the requested data, PLI will not be able to allow the player to play any National Lottery game online.

Direct marketing activity is subject to player consent. The player has the clear option to opt-in to receive marketing communications at registration time and then to opt-out any time.

**Sharing of personal data**

Personal Data is shared with the same organisations as outlined in the Player Registration section above.

The marketing activities outlined in the section above are carried out on an ongoing basis with player consent.

#### Android and iOS Apps

**Personal data processed**

Geo-location, name, IP address, phone device ID, device IMEI, platform, purchase total, device OS version

**Purpose for processing and uses of the data**

Location is required to comply with legal requirements (living in and playing from Ireland).

**Lawful basis for processing the data**

The processing of data is necessary to enter into a contract with PLI and to meet the legal and regulatory requirements of the National Lottery Act and the Licence to Operate the National Lottery.

If the player does not provide the requested data, PLI will not be able to allow the player to play any National Lottery game online.

**Sharing of personal data**

Personal Data is shared with the same organisations as outlined in the Player Registration section above.

The marketing activities outlined above are carried out on an ongoing basis with player consent.

#### Customer Support

**Personal data processed**

Name, email, twitter account, Facebook Messenger account, Instagram account, phone recordings, instant messages

**Purpose for processing and uses of the data**

To provide assistance to players and to monitor quality of services.

**Lawful basis for processing the data**

The processing of data is necessary to enter into a contract with PLI and to meet the legal and regulatory requirements of the National Lottery Act and the Licence to Operate the National Lottery.

If the player does not provide the requested data, PLI will not be able to provide player support.

**Sharing of personal data**

PLI shares personal data with:

  * Camelot Global Services (CGS): management of PLI digital channels, customer care, IT.
  * Intralot Ireland Limited (Intralot): maintenance of PLI’s players and retailers handling platforms and retailer terminals. Intralot staff are based on PLI premises.
  * Comapi who provides our web chat facility. Comapi stores data in locations in North and West Europe.
  * PLI use Conversocial to centrally manage the social media interaction with players. Conversocial stores data outside the EEA, in the USA. (EU-US Privacy Shield). Conversocial is a provider of social customer service software which is used to manage the flow of customer service inquiries and discussions on the National Lottery’s social media channels such as Facebook, twitter, Instagram and YouTube.

#### Winners

**Personal data processed**

Claim forms including: name, address date of birth, telephone number, proof of ID, signature, gender, occupation, and consent for publicity (photographs) which is gathered on a voluntary basis.

**Purpose for processing and uses of the data**

To comply with legal and regulatory requirements (over 18 and responsible player).

For winners above €500, or wallets exceeding €750, payment is made by cheque.

**Lawful basis for processing the data**

The processing of data is necessary to enter into a contract with PLI and to meet the legal and regulatory requirements of the National Lottery Act and the Licence to Operate the National Lottery. If the player does not provide the requested data, PLI will not be able to pay the player.

Publicity material is processed on the basis of consent. Once the information has been passed to the press, PLI would not be able to fulfil requests to withdraw consent.

Gender and occupation information and photograph usage permission are gathered on a voluntary basis.

**Sharing of personal data**

Personal data used to write the cheques is not shared with third parties.

Gender and occupation are extracted from the form and anonymised in a statistics database. The form is kept in secure storage for a duration specified in the Data Retention Policy.

If the player, or syndicate, consents to publicity, the name, winnings and photograph may be published on the National Lottery website, via email and social channels and shared with the press. It will also be archived for future “throwback” marketing purposes.

#### Scratch Card Draw Entries & TV Game Show

**Personal data processed**

Scratch card draw entries: name, address, email address, telephone number and signature.

TV Game Show participants and proxy participants: name, address, date of birth, phone number, signature, type of ID and serial number; proxy participant’s name, address & phone number; photographic and TV broadcast imagery.

Beneficiaries of National Lottery funding: video footage of Good Cause funding recipients and their projects.

**Purpose for processing and uses of the data**

To claim scratch card prizes above a certain value as described in the Game Rules.

To participate on the TV Game Show, or to allow a nominated proxy to participate instead, and for winners to receive prizes.

To publicise the benefits and beneficiaries of Good Cause funding raised by the National Lottery.

**Lawful basis for processing the data**

The processing of data is necessary to enter into a contract with PLI and to meet the legal and regulatory requirements of the National Lottery Act and the Licence to Operate the National Lottery. If the player does not provide the requested data, PLI will not be able to pay the player. If a potential participant of the TV Game Show does not provide the requested data, the potential participant will not be able to take part in the TV Game Show.

Publicity material is processed on the basis of consent. Once the information has been released to the media, PLI would not be able to fulfil requests to withdraw consent.

**Sharing of personal data**

PLI share personal data with

  * RTÉ for TV Game Show production purposes
  * KPMG during independent observation of draws
  * General and selected media and press for publicity purposes
  * The public, where limited personal data is publicly announced on the website, and also on the TV Game Show, where the participants drawn for next week’s show are announced.

#### Second Chance Database

**Personal data processed**

Name, address, date of birth, telephone number, IP address

**Purpose for processing and uses of the data**

To register a retail or online National Lottery Player’s entry into a second chance draw in compliance with legal requirements (over 18 and responsible player).

To send information about offers and promotion.

The information is used internally by the National Lottery's digital marketing team.

**Lawful basis for processing the data**

The processing of data is necessary to enter into a contract with PLI and to meet the legal and regulatory requirements of the National Lottery Act and the Licence to Operate the National Lottery. If the player does not provide the requested data, PLI will not be able to complete the player registration for the relevant second chance draw.

Direct marketing activity is subject to player consent. The player has the clear option to opt-in to receive marketing communications at registration time and then to opt-out any time.

**Sharing of personal data**

PLI share personal data with:

  * Action Point, who create the website in a National Lottery controlled Microsoft Azure server located in North Europe
  * Google Analytics is used to measure the traffic on the second chance website. (EU-US Privacy Shield)
  * HubSpot for marketing campaigns. HubSpot store personal data outside the EEA in the USA. (EU-US Privacy Shield)

#### National Lottery Good Causes Awards

**Personal data processed**

Name, address, email, IP address  
Optional: landline and mobile number

**Purpose for processing and uses of the data**

To go through a competition application process to recognise the inspiring and innovative work being carried out by thousands of individuals, organisations, groups and sports clubs all over Ireland who benefit from National Lottery Good Causes funding. The data will be used to contact and respond to entrants as appropriate.

The information is used internally by National Lottery's marketing team.

**Lawful basis for processing the data**

The processing of data is necessary to enter the competition which the company has a legitimate interest in promoting.

No direct marketing activity will be carried out with the information provided, however, entrants may be contacted with regard to future Good Causes Awards competitions.

**Sharing of personal data**

PLI share personal data with:

  * Connector, who create and host the website where the competition entries are made. The server is located in North Europe.

* * *

Note: The EU-US Privacy Shield imposes obligations on U.S. companies to protect Europeans’ personal data. The Privacy Shield requires the U.S. to monitor and enforce data protection measures, and to cooperate with European Data Protection Authorities.
